Guide to the Tangren Alexander papers Coll 746
University of Oregon Libraries, Special Collections and University Archives
Tangren Alexander papers
1916-2023
University of Oregon Libraries, Special Collections and University Archives
Alexander, Jean Tangren, 1940-2021
Alexander, Marcella
Ní Aódagaín, H.
Corinne, Tee, 1943-2006
Southern Oregon Women Writers' Group, Gourmet Eating Society and Chorus
Coll 746
28.75 linear feet 21 containers 16 record storage boxes; 2 flat boxes; 1 flip-top photo box; 1 photo box; 1 half-manuscript box
Tangren Alexander (1940-2021) was a lesbian feminist philosopher, professor, writer, and doll photographer. The papers include correspondence; writings; teaching materials; event, workshop, and conference materials; doll photography; personal papers; and works by others.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to the public. Collection must be used in Special Collections and University Archives Reading Room. Collection or parts of collection may be stored offsite. Please contact Special Collections and University Archives in advance of your visit to allow for transportation time.
Access to the correspondence series folder "O'Sullivan, Sherry, 1988" is closed until 2063 due to the presence of student records of a third-party individual.
Access to the correspondence series folder ""Oswaldo," international foster child, 1971-1976" is closed until 2061 due to the presence of child welfare records.
Access to the correspondence series folder "Siegel, Thyme, 1988" is closed until 2063 due to the presence of student records of a third-party individual.
Access to the personal papers series folder ""Karen Dudenhoeffer interview of me," 1997" is closed until 2072 due to the presence of student records of a third-party individual.
Conditions Governing Technical Access
Collection includes sound recordings, moving images, and digital files to which access is restricted. Access to these materials is governed by repository policy and may require the production of listening or viewing copies. Researchers requiring access must notify Special Collections and University Archives in advance and pay fees for reproduction services as necessary.
Biographical / Historical
Tangren Alexander (1940-2021) was a lesbian feminist philosopher, professor, writer, and doll photographer.
Dr. Jean Tangren Alexander was born October 22, 1940, in Medford, Oregon, and raised by her parents Chester and Jessie Fitch in Ashland, Oregon. She attended several colleges and received a B.A. in mathematics, an M.A. in philosophy from the University of Oregon, and became the first woman to receive a Ph.D. in philosophy from the University of Oregon in 1975. She was a professor of philosophy at Southern Oregon University from 1974 to 2006. She taught and developed a variety of courses, including cross-disciplinary courses in women's studies, such as Feminism & Philosophy and Women & Ethics. She was married to Southern Oregon University faculty colleague John Alexander, with whom she had a daughter, Marcella. The couple separated in the 1970s.
In 1976, Alexander came out as a lesbian and began a prolific writing career. She produced a voluminous amount of writing in a variety of forms, both published and unpublished. Her writing has been published in Teaching Philosophy; Hypatia: The Journal of Feminist Philosophy; Sinister Wisdom; WomanSpirit Magazine; The Encyclopedia of Women in World History; Adventures in Lesbian Philosophy, Claudia Card, ed.; and Our Lives: Lesbian Personal Writing, Frances Rooney, ed. Under the pseudonym "Pearl Time'sChild," she was the author of short stories in several of Tee Corrine's erotic anthologies. The actor Deborah Kerr was a lifelong muse for Alexander and was a frequent topic of her writing.
Alexander was active in the lesbian land movement community and the creative women's community in Southern Oregon. She was a co-founding member of the Southern Oregon Women Writers' Group, Gourmet Eating Society, and Chorus, which continues to this day.
Having been interested in dolls her entire life, Alexander spent much of her later years photographing dolls and using doll photography to portray feminist stories.
Alexander died at her home in Ashland, Oregon, on March 26, 2021.
Scope and Contents
The Tangren Alexander papers document Alexander's work as a lesbian feminist philosopher, professor, writer, and doll photographer. The papers include correspondence; writings; teaching materials; event, workshop, and conference materials; doll photography; personal papers; and works by others.
The correspondence series contains incoming and outgoing personal and professional correspondence. This series includes letters, printed emails, postcards, and greeting cards, as well as enclosed photographs, documents, and ephemera.
The writings series contains drafts, manuscripts, notes, mockups, publications, correspondence, and working files related to Alexander's literary works. This series includes book-length writings, article and short-story-length writings, poetry and music, notes and fragments, chronological files, and material about publishing.
The teaching material series contains course materials, Northwest Women's Studies Association directories, a poster, and office artifacts from Alexander's time as a philosophy and women's studies professor.
The events, workshops, and conferences series contains notes, writings, flyers, correspondence, and ephemera from workshops, conferences, readings, and other events that Alexander participated in or attended. This series includes drafts of Alexander's writings that were read or presented at events and gatherings.
The doll photography series contains photographic prints, slides, and negatives from doll photography projects. This series also includes albums, homemade books, scripts, notes, writings, and ephemera related to doll photography. A significant portion of the material is related to the "Selene" project.
The personal papers series contains material related to Alexander's personal life. This series includes biographical material, journals, student material, ephemera, and photographs.
The work by others series contains published and unpublished writings, art, and audiovisual materials collected by Alexander. This series includes Southern Oregon Women Writers' Group material, Tee Corinne material, and collected writings and clippings.
Existence and Location of Copies
Selected items are available online in the Tangren Alexander Papers in the Internet Archive.
Arrangement
The Tangren Alexander papers are arranged in seven series:
1. Correspondence, 1935-2020
2. Writings, circa 1950-2020, undated
3. Teaching material, circa 1988-2001, undated
4. Events, workshops, and conferences, circa 1977-2020, undated
5. Doll photography, circa 1990-2012, undated
6. Personal papers, circa 1943-2023, undated
7. Work by others, 1916-2021, undated
Series 1. Correspondence is arranged in two subseries:
1.1. By correspondent, 1968-2017
1.2. By date, 1935-2020
Series 2. Writings is arranged in six subseries:
2.1. Book length, circa 1980-2009, undated
2.2. Article and short story length, 1976-2016, undated
2.3. Poetry and music, circa 1974-1998, undated
2.4. Notes and fragments, circa 1950-2020, undated
2.5. Chronological files, 1974-2018
2.6. Material about publishing, circa 1978-2010, undated
Series 6. Personal papers is arranged in five subseries:
6.1. Biographical material, circa 1943-2023, undated
6.2. Journals, circa 1953-2020
6.3. Student material, 1948-1989
6.4. Ephemera, circa 1950-2020, undated
6.5. Photographs, circa 1950-2010, undated
Series 7. Work by others is arranged in three subseries:
7.1. Southern Oregon Women Writers' Group, 1983-2021, undated
7.2. Tee Corinne material, circa 1968-2008, undated
7.3. Collected writings and clippings, 1916-2020, undated
Related Materials
Related materials are found in the following collections:
Southern Oregon Lesbian Land Communities Oral History Collection (Coll 429).
Ruth Mountaingrove papers (Coll 309).
Tee A. Corinne papers (Coll 263).
SO CLAP! (Southern Oregon Country Lesbian Archival Project) Collection (Coll 266).
Tangren Alexander publications (MSS.058), Southern Oregon University, Hannon Library.
Tangren Alexander papers (MSS.066), Southern Oregon University, Hannon Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Tangren Alexander estate and Marcella Alexander, 2021-2023.
Gift of H. Ní Aódagaín, 2023.
Feminism; Lesbian community -- Oregon; Lesbians -- Oregon; Lesbians' writings; Philosophy -- Study and teaching; Women college teachers -- United States; Women authors, American -- 20th century; dolls; Alexander, Marcella; Alexander, Jean Tangren, 1940-2021; Ní Aódagaín, H.; Kerr, Deborah, 1921-2007
- Correspondence, 1935-2020; 1.
  Arrangement
  Series 1. Correspondence is arranged in two subseries:
  1.1. By correspondent, 1968-2017
  1.2. By date, 1935-2020
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence series contains incoming and outgoing personal and professional correspondence. This series includes letters, printed emails, postcards, and greeting cards, as well as enclosed photographs, documents, and ephemera. Tangren Alexander organized a portion of her correspondence by correspondent and the other portion by date.
  - By correspondent, 1968-2017; 1.1.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent last name, organization name, or subject.
    The by correspondent subseries contains incoming and outgoing personal and professional correspondence. This subseries includes letters, printed emails, postcards, and greeting cards, as well as enclosed photographs, documents, and ephemera.
    - "Archives / libraries", 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Blue Heron, Hannah, 1983-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Corbin, Joan, 1968-1983 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Drabek, Karen Marie, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    - Forest, Shelly, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Gidlow, Elsa, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Harbuck, Deborah, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - HerBooks, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hypatia: A Journal of Feminist Philosophy, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
    - International Dark-Sky Association, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Kerr, Deborah, circa 1970s - 2007 (Box 1, Folder 15-20)
    - Kerr, Deborah, "things I didn't send her", circa 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Kerr, Deborah, "unsent letters", circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lazer, Christina, 1993 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Libré, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Mattel, Inc., 2004 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "The media", 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - O'Sullivan, Sherry, 1976-2001 (Box 1, Folder 27-40)
    - O'Sullivan, Sherry, 1988 (Restricted box 21, Folder 1)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Access to the folder "O'Sullivan, Sherry, 1988" is closed until 2063 due to the presence of student records of a third-party individual.
    - "Oswaldo," international foster child, 1971-1976 (Restricted box 21, Folder 2)
      Access to the folder ""Oswaldo," international foster child, 1971-1976" is closed until September 2061 due to the presence of child welfare records.
    - Overman, Caroline, 1984-2017 (Box 1, Folder 41-49)
    - Payne, Karen, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Ramstetter, Victoria, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Siegel, Thyme, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Siegel, Thyme, 1988 (Restricted box 21, Folder 3)
      Access to the folder "Siegel, Thyme, 1988" is closed until 2063 due to the presence of student records of a third-party individual.
    - Society for the Study of Women Philosophers, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Thomas, Linda, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Verbieren, Narda, 2003 April (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Verbieren, Trudy, 1981-2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "We'Moon", 1997-2010 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Yorkin Publications, 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - By date, 1935-2020; 1.2.
    This subseries is arranged chronologically.
    The by date subseries contains incoming and outgoing personal and professional correspondence. This subseries includes letters, printed emails, postcards, and greeting cards, as well as enclosed photographs, documents, and ephemera.
    - 1935-2020 (Box 2, Folder 11-38, Box 3, Folder 1-36)
- Writings, circa 1950-2020, undated; 2.
  Series 2. Writings is arranged in six subseries:
  2.1. Book length, circa 1980-2009, undated
  2.2. Article and short story length, 1976-2016, undated
  2.3. Poetry and music, circa 1974-1998, undated
  2.4. Notes and fragments, circa 1950-2020, undated
  2.5. Chronological files, 1974-2018
  2.6. Material about publishing, circa 1978-2010, undated
  The writings series contains drafts, manuscripts, notes, mockups, publications, correspondence, and working files related to Alexander's literary works. This series includes book-length writings, article and short-story-length writings, poetry and music, notes and fragments, chronological files, and material about publishing.
  The book length subseries contains drafts, manuscripts, notes, mockups, bound volumes, and correspondence related to Alexander's book-length writings, including The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr; Her Majesty, The King: Queen Christina of Sweden; and Tenderly: A Lesbian Remembrance of Deborah Kerr. This subseries also contains material related to recordings Alexander made of herself reading her writings aloud.
  The article and short story length subseries contains handwritten and typed drafts, manuscripts, notes, correspondence, and publications related to Alexander's article and short-story-length writings. In addition to articles and short stories, this subseries includes anthology contributions, diary entries intended for publication, and published excerpts from longer works.
  The poetry and music subseries contains handwritten and typed drafts of poetry and songs written by Alexander.
  The notes and fragments subseries contains notes and fragments of writing that may or may not have been incorporated in Alexander's other works.
  The chronological files subseries consists of files kept by Alexander, arranged by year, containing miscellaneous writings, notes, literary work, journal entries, letters, incoming and outgoing correspondence, and ephemera.
  The material about publishing subseries contains notes and collected information about the publishing industry, as well as material related to the printing and publishing of Alexander's literary works.
  First drafts of many of Alexander's writings can be found in her handwritten journals in subseries 6.2. Journals.
  Material related to Alexander's writings can also be found in series 4. Events, workshops, and conferences.
  - Book length, circa 1980-2009, undated; 2.1.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by file title.
    The book length subseries contains drafts, manuscripts, notes, mockups, bound volumes, and correspondence related to Alexander's book-length writings, including The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, Her Majesty, The King: Queen Christina of Sweden, and Tenderly: A Lesbian Remembrance of Deborah Kerr. This subseries also contains material related to recordings Alexander made of herself reading her writings aloud, including an audio version of her book Tenderly: A Lesbian Remembrance of Deborah Kerr and CDs that Alexander made to give to Deborah Kerr.
    - The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, bound volume, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, distribution notes, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, earlier drafts", undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, extra graphics", undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, Faith Yates correspondence, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, handwritten unbound volume, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, mock-ups, undated (Box 17, Folder 2-4)
    - "The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, original reductions", circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - "The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, part I", undated (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - "The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, part II", undated (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
    - The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, permissions letters, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr, typed Claris version", undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - "CD for Deborah, latest versions", 2005 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - "CD/Tape for Deborah Kerr," notes, CDs, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      This file includes digital materials to which access is restricted. Access to these materials is governed by repository policy and may require the production of listening or viewing copies. Researchers requiring access must notify Special Collections and University Archives in advance and pay fees for reproduction services as necessary.
    - "D. K. poetry reading", 2009 May 21 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Deborah Kerr as literature", undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "Deborah Kerr tapes, notes", undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "Haworth Press book proposal", 2003 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Her Majesty, The King, "Astraea grant", 1992 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - "Her Majesty, The King, office version, last worked on 11/93", 1993 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - A House of One's Own, mock-up, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Kristina, So Far, 1993 May, undated (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
    - "Kristina, So Far, large originals with next changes", 1993 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - "Kristina, So Far, My Voice," notes, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "Kristina, So Far, new writing", 1993 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "Kristina, So Far, old versions", 1989-1991 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - "Kristina, So Far, older version, ideas", circa 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Kristina, So Far, version 1, annotated, booklets, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - "Kristina, So Far, with pictures", undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - "Magic and Philosophy," manuscript, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - "Making Tea and Sympathy tape", circa 2001 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - "Music for Deborah Kerr CD?", circa 2006 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - My Mother's People, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 35-36)
    - My Mother's People, bound volume, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - "Next on DK writing, recording", undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Next tape for Deborah", circa 2005 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Palimpsests and Mirrors, mock-up, circa 1980s (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - "Playlists for tapes", circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Readings for Tea and Sympathy tape", circa 2001 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Ruth Baldwin Chenery, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - Ruth Baldwin Chenery, bound volume, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Ruth Baldwin Chenery, notes, circa 1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Sense and Sensimilla, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Sense and Sinsemilla, mock-up, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Tenderly: Lesbian Meditations on Deborah Kerr, circa 2001, undated (Box 5, Folder 10-16)
    - "Tenderly, Alice Street Editions," correspondence, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - "Tenderly, CD labels", undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - "Tenderly, cover, boxset", undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - "Tenderly, front and back covers", undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - "Tenderly: A Lesbian Remembrance of Deborah Kerr, book notes", circa 2008, undated (Box 5, Folder 21-24)
    - "Tenderly: A Lesbian Remembrance of Deborah Kerr, foldered version", undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - "Tenderly: A Lesbian Remembrance of Deborah Kerr, printed sideways", 2009 June 7 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - "Tenderly, recording it", undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - "Tenderly, sideways, current, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - "Tenderly, sort", circa 2002-2007 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Article and short story length, 1976-2016, undated; 2.2.
    - "Alexa," "Scents and nonsense", undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - "April Wednesday", undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - "Aunt Sarah", 1982-1989 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - "Barbie article", 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - "The Box", 1978-1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 34-35)
    - "The Box," drafts, circa 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - "Can Grownups Play Dolls?", 1997 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - "Can 2 Girls Get Married", 2007 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - "Celebrating the 4%", unated (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - "The Changeling", 1985-1993 (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
    - "The Changeling," booklet, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - "The Changeling," "Kali Lullaby," Hypatia submission, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - "Christina of Sweden," Women in World History: A Biographical Encyclopedia, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - "The Columbia Hotel", undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - "Contracts, letters for pieces in Anthologies", 1990-1993 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - "Coyote woman," "Women's class teaching dreams", 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - "Death and vision", 1984-1990 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - "Deborah Carr", 1996 (Box 5, Folder 49-50)
    - "Doll papers to file", undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - "Dreams of Deborah Kerr in the months preceding her death", 2007 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - "End pieces", circa 2006 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - "Est et Non: The Dream Body", circa 1980s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
    - "Finding the Founding Mother", 1988 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - "Friendship Street, Karen", undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - "The Ho Journal, as typed up 12/94", 1994 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - "Hypatia reprints", 1992 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - "Hypatia submission, poster, Sophie Brahe, Motherphysics," correspondence, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Hypatia submissions, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - "Inside the DMV," "Gay Pride Day Evening," "Catherine", undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - "January 1980", 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 63-64)
    - "January 1980: Journal Excerpts from The Auto Biography of Deborah Carr" (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - ""January 1980," typed", 1986 August 8 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - "Karen as Literature", 2003 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - "Latihan article," "Going mad/sane", circa 1982 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - "Letters and Dreams", circa 2013 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - "Making a Book", 1991 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - "Making/Sending Her a Tape", 2000 August 8 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - "Mary Pearce", undated (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - "Mary Spear", 1982 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - ""Mary Spear," as short story," "Aunt Sarah", 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - "Motherphysics", undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - "Movies and Metaphysics", undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - "Mu Beach", 1995-1997 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - "Mu Beach, or How I Encountered A Coven of Lesbianated Wild Nuns and What We Did Then", undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - "Mu 21", 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "My D and D writing, originals", undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - "My writing / showing Selene," essays, poems, teaching material, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - "Ninian Smart", 1997 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "October 13 or A Theory", 1980 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - ""One August," typed", 1982-1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - "One Woman's Day is Another Woman's Dawn", 1977 Spring - 1977 Summer (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - "The O'Sullivan Saga and other journal entries", 1988 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "Other Lives", 1983 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - "The Raga Dianne, originals", 1982 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - "Raga for Dianne and Explanations Later", undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - "Rattlesnake", circa 1999 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - "Rattlesnake story, etc.", 1992 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - "Reading for Faculty '97 - possibilities", 1997 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - "Remembering Tea and Sympathy", 2013, undated (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
    - ""Remembering Tea and Sympathy," writer's group comments and notes," annotated copies, 2016 Fall (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - "Schrodinger's Cat and Abalone", 1980s (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - "Sex and Death, about Tee Corinne", 2006 (Box 6, Folder 22)